Guide to the Golden Gate Kindergarten Association Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Golden Gate Kindergarten Association records
1878-1991
SC0936
Golden Gate Kindergarten Association (San Francsico, Calif.)
1.5 Linear feet
Collection includes minutes, reports, correspondence, financial records, articles, news clippings, notes, and photographs. Many of the notes and articles are by Rhoda Kellogg, Director of the Association from the early 1940s until her retirement in 1969.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
The Golden Gate Kindergarten Association was founded in 1879 to aid San Francisco’s needy children. Supported by philanthropists Phoebe A. Hearst and Jane Lathrop Stanford and directed by Sarah B. Cooper, the Association had opened 40 kindergartens by 1895. After kindergartens became part of the public schools, the association turned its efforts to pre-school education.
Description of the Collection
Collection includes minutes, reports, correspondence, financial records, articles, news clippings, notes, and photographs. Many of the notes and articles are by Rhoda Kellogg, Director of the Association from the early 1940s until her retirement in 1969.
Access Terms
Golden Gate Kindergarten Association (San Francsico, Calif.); Kellogg, Rhoda, 1898-; Early childhood education--California.; Kindergarten--California.
Collection Contents
- Records
  - A Study of Independent Schools’ Financial Development Policies and Their Practical Application as a Model for Preschool Programs, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Sarah B. Cooper Memorabilia (includes obituary and memorial resolution, 1896) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - GGKA Teaching School Memorabilia, 1882-1926 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - California School History, 1911-1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Child Art Notes (includes articles and reports by Rhoda Kellogg), 1952-1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Community Chest, correspondence and articles, 1927-1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Montessori Reports, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Financial Statements, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hearst Preschool Learning Center, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - GGKA Publications, 1959-1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Synopsis of GGKA History, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Stanford Trust Information, correspondence, 1923-1990 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Historical Material, 1920-1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1943-1990 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Stanford Trust Background: information compiled from reports covering the years 1881-1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Information from Rhoda Kellogg’s Notes, 1967-1990 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Historical Material Stanford, 1906-1974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Historical Material Stanford Trust (includes letter from Virginia Fitch to Timothy Hopkins ca. 1925) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Stanford Will [various copies of the trust deed for the Leland Stanford Jr. Kindergarten Trust], 1891-1976 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Histories, 1907-1940 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - De Kooning Drawing, correspondence re sale of, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Child Care Clippings, 1926-1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Duplicates of First Drafts Child Art, 1951-1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, 1878-ca. 1966 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Stovall, Anna M., letters to and about, 1926 and undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Stanford miscellany: articles, 1899-1929; letter re trust 1964; and attendance roster possibly from Stanford kindergarten, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Old Notes, 1906-1942 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Duplicates, 1953-1985 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Auxiliary minutes, clippings, 1957-1970 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Rhoda Kellogg Publications, 1949-1971 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Rhoda Kellogg’s Research, 1953-1969 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Froebel Society reports and publications, 1880-1897 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Photographs, 1909-1914 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - History, 1915-1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Reports, 1963-1965 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1927-1939 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Leland Stanford Junior Kindergarten Trust, history of with copies of documents, 1917-1991 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - The San Francisco Foundation Annual Report, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, 1941 and undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Rhoda Kellogg, 1954-1977 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Reports, 1883-1973 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Signed Agreement [copies of] re Spring Valley Water Works stock assigned to GGKA, 1894 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - History of Kindergarten Movement in San Francisco, 1902-1949 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - History of Kindergarten Movement in San Francisco, clippings, 1910-1913 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Documents, 1940-1990 (Box 3, Folder 10)